Finding Aid for Center for Global and Intercultural Study (University of Michigan) Records 1964-2004
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Center for Global and Intercultural Study (University of Michigan) Records 1964-2004, 1982-1996
University of Michigan. Center for Global and Intercultural Study.
22 linear feet
Office that administered foreign travel and study programs the University of Michigan; records document administration of program, content of curriculum and student experience.
93819 Bimu/2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group was transferred to the library in different accessions beginning in 1993. Donor no. 8099
The record group is open for research.
In the 1960s, the University of Michigan College of Literature, Science and the Arts established and administered student overseas travel and study programs, including the Junior Year Abroad Program in Aix-en-Provence, France and Freiburg, Germany. In the early 1970s, the college centralized administration of the programs in the Center for Western European Studies (CWES), which received funding for this work from the Ford Foundation. By that time the programs included a joint program with Sarah Lawrence University in London, and the University of Michigan-University of Wisconsin Academic Year Program in Italy, which is situated in Florence. Funding from the Ford Foundation ended in 1977, and the college resumed financial support for the programs. Some university departments organized their own programs. The Romance Languages and Literatures department, for example, supervised two: one at the University of Salamanca in Spain and one at the University of Tours in France. All overseas travel and study programs were directed and staffed by senior faculty from Michigan or from the cooperating institutions.
In 1983, CWES was reorganized and given control over all international study programs, including those in departments. CWES established an executive committee as the agent to oversee operations, and four other committees to handle various tasks. The committees included: Foreign Study, International Exchange and Fellowships, On-campus Programs, and Colloquia and Conferences. The members of the executive committee included the director and associate director, a past director, and each of the four committee chairs. With this reorganization several new programs were inaugurated, including four in Britain, and one in Paris. The executive committee members in conjunction with the dean of the College of Literature, Science and the Arts appointed the CWES director who served a three-year term.
In 1989, the Office of International Programs (OIP) replaced the Center for Western European Studies as the overseeing agency for study abroad programs. The OIP was later replaced by the Center for Global and Intercultural Study (CGIS), which was founded in July 2009 to provide a wide variety of global engagement and learning opportunities to the University of Michigan Community. Today, the CGIS offers over 70 programs in over 30 countries, serving "students with diverse academic interests at international and domestic sites on every inhabited continent.
For current information on the Center for Global and Intercultural Study consult the unit's web page at the following url: http://www.lsa.umich.edu/cgis
The record group is divided into five series: Background, Administrative Files, Programs, Correspondence, and Photographs.
The records of the Office of International Programs document the development and administration of the University of Michigan's travel abroad and foreign study programs and the content of the program at various sites, particularly Florence, Paris, Aix-en-Provence, London, and Freiburg. Records include committees minutes, correspondence, curricular records, syllabi and student evaluations of the program.
Subjects:
Foreign study--Europe.; Foreign study--Israel.; Student housing--Italy--Florence.; Students--Recreation--France--Aix-en-Provence.; University of Michigan. Center for Global and Intercultural Study.; University of Michigan. Office of International Programs.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Dwellings--Italy--Florence.
Contributors:
University of Michigan. Center for Global and Intercultural Study.; University of Michigan. Office of International Programs.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Background
  The Background series (1991-1997, 12 folders) provides a brief introduction to Center for Western European Studies (CWES) and OIP activities. These files include an outline of CWES' main areas of development since 1977, an administrative structure outline of CWES, and information and publicity materials compiled for students about the various OIP programs and about foreign study opportunities in general. This material is housed in boxes 1, 8, 13, and 19.
  - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous 1992-1994 (Box 8)
  - Publicity Information 1991-1994, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Program forms and admission letters 1987 (Box 8)
  - Program information and brochures 1997 (Box 8)
  - Program forms and scholarships 1995 (Box 13)
  - General Program Information 1995-1996, 3 folders (Box 19)
- Administrative Files
  The Administrative Files series (1969-1997, 20 folders) includes files of different office committees. Within the minutes of meetings of the executive committee are discussions about establishing new programs and changing existing ones. There are also committee discussions of the nomination of new directors for the various programs and the work of the current staff. The files also include reports on individual programs, reports on faculty and staff, and proposals for establishing new programs and improving existing ones
  - Executive Committee 1969-1988, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Staff Meeting Agenda 1992-1993 (Box 1)
  - Steering Committee 1988-1994, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Advisory Committee 1990 (Box 1)
  - Report of the Committee for the Review of OIP 1991 (Box 1)
  - Reports 1973-1974 (Box 1)
  - Committee on Lectures and Conferences 1986 (Box 1)
  - Student Advisory Board (Box 13)
  - Steering Committee 1994-1997, 3 folders (Box 13)
  - Organizational Reports 1990-1992, 2 folders (Box 13)
- Programs
  The Programs series (1964-2004, 20 linear feet) is an alphabetical arrangement of files on the programs administered by CWES and OIP. The programs in Florence, Paris, Aix-en-Provence, London, and Freidburg comprise the bulk of this series, which is the largest series in the collection. Documents found include student orientation material, student evaluations of the programs, directors' reports, budgetary information, faculty reports, course descriptions and syllabi, meeting minutes, policy and procedure statements, faculty position descriptions, and general correspondence. General correspondence includes legal, fiscal and disciplinary action issues. This material is housed in boxes 1-7 and 9-22.
  - Agreements and Contracts 1980s (Box 13)
  - Aix-en-Provence
    - 1966-1988 (Box 1)
    - 1966-1988 (cont.) (Box 2)
    - 1984-1998, 11 folders (Box 8)
    - 1994-1997, 7 folders (Box 13)
  - Arabic Studies 1978-1980 (Box 2)
  - Australia 1991-1996, 5 folders (Box 13)
  - Brazil 2002, 4 folders (Box 14)
  - Chile
    - Undated (Box 2)
    - 1992-1994, 6 folders (Box 9)
    - 1992-1996, 4 folders (Box 13)
    - 1996-2002, 8 folders (Box 14)
    - 1990-2001, 6 folders (Box 15)
  - China
    - 1995 (Box 13)
    - 1990-2000, 15 folders (Box 18)
    - 1988-1995, 7 folders (Box 19)
  - Costa Rica
    - 1997 (Box 13)
    - 2000-2004 (Box 15)
  - Cuba 2002-2004, 3 folders (Box 15)
  - Denmark 1982-1983 (Box 2)
  - Dijon 1979 (Box 2)
  - Dominican Republic
    - 1995-1997, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - 1996-2002, 11 folders (Box 15)
  - Eastern and Central Europe (Poland, Czech Republic, Hungary) 1996-1997 (Box 13)
  - Eastern and Southern Asia Program 1997-1998 (Box 19)
  - Ecuador
    - 1994-1996, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - 1996-2000, 7 folders (Box 15)
    - 1999-2001, 11 folders (Box 16)
  - Florence
    - Undated (Box 2)
    - 1970-1993 (Box 3)
    - 1970-1993 (Box 4)
    - 1985-1997, 44 folders (Box 9)
    - 1985-1997, 7 folders (Box 10)
    - 1992-2002, 9 folders (Box 13)
  - Freidburg
    - 1964-1993, 35 folders (Box 5)
    - 1992-1994, 11 folders (Box 10)
    - 1993-1997, 3 folders (Box 13)
  - Ghana
    - 1993 (Box 10)
    - 1990-1996, 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Grenada 2000 (Box 16)
  - India Site Seminar
    - 1990-1993 (Box 11)
    - 1993 (Box 13)
  - Ireland 1995-1997, 3 folders (Box 13)
  - Israel 1982-1985, 5 folders (Box 5)
  - Jamaica
    - Undated (Box 5)
    - 1993-1995, 5 folders (Box 11)
    - 1995-1996, 2 folders (Box 14)
  - Japan
    - 1994-1996, 3 folders (Box 14)
    - 1993-1996, 5 folders (Box 20)
    - Japan Center for Michigan Universities 1989-1993, 4 folders (Box 11)
    - Japan Center for Michigan Universities 1993-1999, 17 folders (Box 20)
    - Kyoto Center for Japanese Studies 1986-1993, 13 folders (Box 11)
    - Kyoto Center for Japanese Studies 1986-1993, 7 folders (Box 11)
    - Kyoto Center for Japanese Studies 1988-1999, 12 folders (Box 21)
    - Kyushu 1995-2000, 11 folders (Box 21)
    - Tokyo 1997-1998, 3 folders (Box 21)
    - Tokyo 1995-2000, 3 folders (Box 22)
  - Junior Year Abroad, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Karl Franzens Universitat 1983 (Box 5)
  - Korea
    - EWHA Women’s University 1994 (Box 14)
    - 1996-2000, 10 folders (Box 19)
    - 1993-2000, 6 folders (Box 20)
  - London, Sarah Lawrence-University of Michigan 1976-1987, 19 folders (Box 6)
  - Mexico
    - 1995-1996 (Box 14)
    - 1992-2000, 5 folders (Box 16)
  - Museum of Art Visit 1985 (Box 6)
  - Nice 1971 (Box 6)
  - Novacello (Box 6)
  - Paris 1982-1989, 16 folders (Box 6)
  - Poggio a Caiano Symposium 1985 (Box 6)
  - Poland Exchange Information 1983 (Box 6)
  - Poland
    - 1991 (Box 14)
    - 1993 (Box 11)
  - Quebec
    - 1979 (Box 6)
    - 1990-1995 (Box 14)
  - Rome 1995-1997 (Box 14)
  - Russia, American Collegiate Consortium 1995-1996 (Box 11)
  - Russia 1990-1996, 2 folders (Box 14)
  - Saint Malo (France)
    - 1991-1993, 6 folders (Box 12)
    - 1993 (Box 14)
  - Saudi Arabia 1983-1984 (Box 6)
  - Scandinavia 1982-1984 (Box 6)
  - Smithsonian 1983-1986 (Box 6)
  - Southeast Asia 1994-1996 (Box 14)
  - Spain
    - Undated, 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Barcelona
      - 1970-1971 (Box 6)
      - 1996 (Box 14)
      - 1996 (Box 16)
    - Salamanca/Seville
      - 1984-1992 (Box 6)
      - 1984-1992 (cont.) (Box 7)
    - Salamanca
      - 1992-1993, 4 folders (Box 12)
      - 1995 (Box 14)
      - 1993-2002, 13 folders (Box 16)
      - 2002-2003, 7 folders (Box 17)
    - Santander
      - 1998 (Box 14)
      - 1998, 4 folders (Box 17)
    - Seville
      - 1992-1994, 13 folders (Box 12)
      - 1986-1998, 9 folders (Box 14)
      - 1996-2000, 10 folders (Box 17)
      - 2000-2003, 7 folders (Box 18)
  - Switzerland -- Lausanne 1994-1996 (Box 14)
  - Taiwan 1997-2000, 7 folders (Box 22)
  - Tours 1985-1988, 4 folders (Box 7)
  - Tuebingen, Germany
    - 1974-1986 (Box 7)
    - 1992-1993 (Box 12)
    - Undated (Box 14)
  - Turkey (Istanbul) 1996 (Box 14)
  - Turku (Finland)
    - 1991-1994 (Box 12)
    - 1991-1994 (Box 14)
  - United Kingdom
    - General
      - 1986 (Box 7)
      - 1991-1992 (Box 12)
      - 1988-1997 (Box 14)
    - Cambridge (Box 7)
    - Essex
      - 1992 (Box 7)
      - 1993 (Box 12)
    - London
      - 1992-1993, 5 folders (Box 12)
      - 1991-1997, 2 folders (Box 14)
      - London School of Economics, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Oxford
      - St. Peters 1989-1991 (Box 7)
      - 1993-1995, 6 folders (Box 12)
      - 1997 (Box 14)
    - St. Andrews
      - Undated, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - 1991-1992 (Box 12)
    - Sussex
      - 1975 1978 (Box 7)
      - 1993-1994 (Box 12)
    - University College of London 1977-1984 (Box 7)
    - York 1983, 1992, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Uppsala (Sweden)
    - 1984-1989, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - 1992-1993 (Box 12)
    - 1993-1997 (Box 14)
  - Yeats Festival 1977-1980, 2 folders (Box 7)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series (1977-1997, 40 folders) concerns the internal workings of the programs. Many of the letters are incoming and outgoing from the directors' or associate directors' office and detail aspects of operations and administrative matters. Also included are letters discussing potential joint programs with various institutions in the United States and abroad.
  - Chronological
    - 1977-1988 1992, 18 folders (Box 7)
    - 1987-1997, 11 folders (Box 14)
  - Program Correspondence
    - Internal Programs 1986-1988 (Box 7)
    - External Programs 1984-1987, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Directors' Correspondence
    - Mary Crichton September 1988-August 1990 (Box 7)
    - Ralph Williams January 1989-June 1989 (Box 8)
    - James Cather July 1988-June 1992, 6 folders (Box 8)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series (undated, 3 folders) has nineteen black and white, 8" x 10" interior photographs of the Villa Boscobello, used as the residence in Florence for the University of Michigan - University of Wisconsin Academic Year Program in Italy. There is, in addition, a folder with seven black and white, 5" x 7" photographs of a student gathering in Aix-en-Provence.
  - Villa Boscobello, Florence, 19, 8"x10" b/w images of Villa interior (Box 8)
  - Students, Aix-en-Provence, 7, 5"x7" b/w images of groups (Box 8)
  - Spain (Seville), 5 color images (Box 18)